Samantha Pendleton BSc MSc

IT GRADUATE | DATA SCIENTIST | PhDc CLINICAL INFORMATICS

BIRMINGHAM, B17 0JN samanfapendle@outlook.com



github.com/sap218



twitter.com/sap218

PROFILE

Currently a PhD student in Clinical Informatics/Bioinformatics after completing my Masters postgraduate degree in Data Science. I have an extensive set of skills, ranging from data science applications, bioinformatics, IT and business. I am an organised individual, who works well through fast-paced environments, able to communicate effectively with colleagues. I have strong experience in assisting individuals, specifically students, throughout my employment and educational practises.

SKILLS

DATA SCIENCE

Bioinformatics, Statistics, Data Mining Machine Learning, Ontologies, Text Mining

BUSINESS

System Analyst, Business Planning, Visualisation, Communication, and Presentation

LANGUAGES

Python & R; HTML, CSS, & PHP; SQL: PostgreSQL, SQLite, & NoSQL

IT

Administration, Operating Systems Cyber Security, Countless Software

PROJECTS

» Metagenomics of Acid Soil – a study of long reads

Postgraduate Masters Dissertation in Bioinformatics/Computational Biology (2018) acidoseq: Python (v3.5) package aimed to study Acidobacteria; available: https://github.com/sap218/acidoseq

» An analysis of current software for nanopore metagenomic data

Bioinformatics Research Project, Summer (2017)

Computer Science department at Aberystwyth University; available: https://doi.org/10.1101/288969

EDUCATION

PhD student in Clinical Informatics (2018+)

Medical School, Institute of Translational Medicine at University of Birmingham

Thesis: "Creating an Al based data assistant to bridge genotype to metadata linking primary clinical data

to biobank sample"

Additional: Machine Learning, Text Mining, Ontologies, Statistics

» Masters graduate in Data Science (2017-18)

Merit - Computer Science Postgraduate (MSc) at Aberystwyth University

Dissertation: "Metagenomics of Acid Soil": acidoseq; PG dissertation: https://github.com/sap218/misc

In fulfilment of the Postgraduate Masters Degree; Computer Science, Aberystwyth University

Additional: Advisor/Demonstrator, President of Computer Science Society

» Bachelors graduate in Business Information Technology (2014-17)

2:1 - Computer Science Undergraduate (BSc) at Aberystwyth University

Dissertation: Web Major Project: The Little Cake Box; UG dissertation: https://github.com/sap218/misc

In fulfilment of the Undergraduate Bachelors Degree; Computer Science, Aberystwyth University

Additional: Demonstrator, Peer Mentor

» **A-levels** (2012-14)

IT (D*D*) Home Economics [Health & Social Care] (M)

Advanced Subsidiary: Mathematics & German

Extra-Curricular: Art

EXPERIENCE

» Researcher, Bioinformatics; Aberystwyth University (2017)

Project: "An analysis of current state of the art software on nanopore metagenomic data"

Bioinformatics Poster: https://github.com/sap218/misc

» Assistant; Information Services at Hugh Owen Library, Aberystwyth University (2016-17)

Jobs: Assisted staff, attended focus groups, made strategy & floor plans

» Student Worker; AberWorks, Aberystwyth University (2016-18)

Jobs: Demonstrator/Advisor, Summer Operative: Ambassador

» Classroom Assistant; Rimrose Hope Primary School (2011)

Jobs: Helped plus guided pupils

Volunteering/Charity Work; educational environments (2006-17)

Jobs: Environmental work, assisted with charity events, aiding the elderly

Peer mentor for the Computer Science Department at Aberystwyth University

ACHIEVEMENTS

» BCS Lovelace Colloquium attendee (2017-18)

- Finalist ('18): An analysis of current software for nanopore metagenomic data

- Attendee ('17): Making websites attractive

Aberystwyth/Sheffield University Women's Conference; posters: https://github.com/sap218/misc

» Manual Handling Course (2016-17)

Certificate from Aberystwyth University

» Diversity Certificate (2016)

Diversity in the workplace training from Aberystwyth University

» Peer Mentor work shadowing volunteer (2016)

Peer Mentor participation at Aberystwyth University; Careers Service Volunteer Work Placement

INTERESTS

I enjoy a wide variety of activities; I appreciate cinematography, reading small fictional novels, and music. Plus, I am keen on puzzles; as such Chess. I enjoy creative hobbies/crafts; having created pillows, paintings, and knitting. Most of my time is spent on personal projects, which I progress during my spare time – I focus on developing my knowledge through these individual ventures and via web browsing. Projects can be found in my GitHub portfolio; with blogs discussing some of these projects can be found in my personal site here: https://sap218.github.io/.

PUBLICATIONS

"An analysis of current state of the art software on nanopore metagenomic data"

Samantha C Pendleton bioRxiv 288969; doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/288969

Note: article is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed

"Metagenomics of Acid Soil; a study of Nanopore long-reads and Acidobacteria"

Samantha C Pendleton, et al. **Note**: article is currently in progress